Vasquez, Richard E. mss., 1960-1990 LMC 2777
Lilly Library
Vasquez, Richard E. mss.
1960-1990
Lilly Library
Vasquez, Richard E., 1928-1990
LMC 2777
6 Boxes 5 standard, 1 custom
The Vasquez, Richard E. mss., 1960-1990, consists of the papers of Chicano author and journalist Richard E. Vasquez, 1928-1990.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 2011
Biographical Note
Richard E. Vasquez, 1928-1990, was a Chicano author and journalist. Vasquez's novel Chicano (Doubleday, 1970) was the first novel about Mexican-Americans released by a major publisher, and it helped establish him as a significant figure on the Chicano literary scene. That same year he began to write regularly for the Los Angeles Times, covering Chicano affairs and human rights issues. Vasquez, who dropped out of high-school to fight in WWII, returned home to work in construction, then began driving a taxi full time. His first stories were human interest newspaper columns based on his experiences as a cabbie. Beginning in 1960, he worked on Chicano for ten years. In spite of his initial success, his subsequent career was marked by struggle and rejection as the notion of "Chicano writing" became increasingly radicalized. Nevertheless, his novel is now considered a classic in the field, and it was reissued in 2005 as a Harper Perennial. In addition to Chicano, he published two other novels, The Giant Killer (1978) and Another Land (1982).
Scope and Content Note
The archive includes a broad range of typescripts, galley proofs, extensive correspondence, contracts, TV proposals, clippings, reviews, and much unpublished material, including a chapter of Chicano not present in the final printed version.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into the following series: I. Writings – Novels, II. Short Stories/Plays, III. Movies/Television, IV. Newspaper, V. Correspondence, VI. Biographical Materials.
Mexican-Americans; American literature -- Mexican American authors; Vasquez, Richard E., 1928-1960
- I. WRITINGS - NOVELS (Box 1)
  - Chicano
    - Typescript – Unpublished Version, (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - Extra Chapter, Unpublished (Box 1)
    - Unassociated Rough Copy Pages (Box 1)
    - Agreement (Box 1)
    - Royalties (Box 1)
    - Reviews (Box 1)
    - Motion Picture Rights (Box 1)
    - Various Chicano Articles (Box 1)
    - Student Term Paper (Box 1)
    - Book Beat, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Oversized: Galleys, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Another Land/Wetback
    - Synopsis (Box 1)
    - Draft, 488 p.p., (4 folders) (Box 1)
    - Draft, 311 p.p. with comments, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Draft, 411 p.p., (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Draft, Chapter (Unused?), 27 p.p. (Box 1)
    - Draft, Chapter (Unused?), 331-377 p.p. (Box 2)
    - Draft, 8 p. (Box 2)
    - Draft with Corrections, p.p. 1-7 (Box 2)
    - Draft with Corrections, p.p. 378-389 (Box 2)
    - Partial Draft, Miscellaneous Pages, 124 p. (Box 2)
    - Partial Draft, Miscellaneous Pages, 116 p. (Box 2)
    - Xerox of Unfinished, Corrected Manuscript, p 1-150A (Box 2)
    - Xerox of Unfinished, Corrected Manuscript, p 151-330 (Box 2)
    - Excerpt, Final Chapter (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Movie or TV Drama Development, 4 p. (Box 2)
    - Notes on Title (Box 2)
  - Giant Killer
    - Synopsis, 2 p. (Box 2)
    - Draft, 311 p.p., (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - Early Draft, Partial 194 p.p., (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Early Draft, Chapter 3, 5 p.p. (Box 2)
    - Early Draft, Chapter 10, 26 p.p. (Box 2)
    - Early Draft, Chapter 1, 8 p.p. (Box 2)
    - Early Draft, Page 1, Version 1 (Box 2)
    - Early Draft, Page 1, Version 2 (Box 2)
    - Early Draft, Partial with Notes, 172 p.p., (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - High Kicker, Sequel to Giant Killer, 1 p.p. (Box 2)
    - Message to Garcia: GK Sequel Outline, 12 p.p. (Box 2)
    - Series Proposal, 25 p.p. (Box 2)
    - Television Series Proposal, 29 p. (Box 2)
    - Agreement (Box 2)
    - Reviews (Box 2)
    - Agreement (Box 2)
    - High Kicker, Miscellaneous Pages, 6 p. (Box 2)
    - A Message to Garcia, Introduction, 1 p. (Box 2)
    - Motion Picture Rights (Box 2)
    - Contract (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - And Then They Shouted Viva!
    - Draft, 112 p. (Box 2)
    - Draft, 221 p., (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Draft, Chapter 1, 3 copies, 31 p. (Box 2)
    - Draft, Chapter 1 Partials, p.p. 1-7, 28, 28 (Box 2)
    - Draft, Miscellaneous Corrected Pages, p.p. 1-100 (Box 3)
    - Draft, Miscellaneous Corrected Pages, p.p. 101-215 (Box 3)
  - Counter-Invasion: A Study of the Mexican-American
    - Xerox Typescript, 31 p. (Box 3)
    - Typescript with Authorial Emendations, 31 p. (Box 3)
    - T.L.S. by Luther Nichols, Editor, October 1984 (Box 3)
    - Draft, Corrected Manuscript, p.p. 22, 23 (Box 3)
    - Draft, Corrected Manuscript, 25 p. (Box 3)
    - Draft, Xerox of Corrected Manuscript, 25 p. (Box 3)
    - Draft, Corrected Manuscript, 21 p. (Box 3)
    - Photocopy, Corrections, 31 p. (Box 3)
    - Draft with Corrections, 26 p. (Box 3)
    - Xerox of Corrected Typed Copy, 25 p. (Box 3)
    - Draft, Incomplete, 19p. (Box 3)
  - Gordon Springer
    - Corrected Manuscript, 1-71 p.p. (Box 3)
    - Gordon Springer, Xerox of Corrected Manuscript, 73 p. (Box 3)
    - Gordon Springer, Second Xerox of Corrected Manuscript, 73 p. (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Novels
    - T.L.S. to Beth, Literary Agent, Proposal, August 1982 (Box 3)
    - Proposal, Whispering Ages, 18 p. (Box 3)
    - T.L.S. from Luther Nichols, Editor – Doubleday, Jan 1984 (Box 3)
    - The Baton, 93 p.p. (Box 3)
    - Plot Outline, Project ERG, 18 p. (Box 3)
    - Synopsis, "A Friend of Einstein, a Novel," 114 p. (Box 3)
    - Outline, "Ben Wilson, a Yankee Amigo," 48 p. (Box 3)
    - Draft, Untitled, p.p. 3-37 (Box 3)
    - Draft, Untitled, 3 p. (Box 3)
    - Draft, "Detective and the General," 8 p. (Box 3)
    - Draft, "Curses of the Three Witches," 3 p. (Box 3)
    - Synopsis, "Desert Assassination," 6 p. (Box 3)
    - Synopsis, Oatman Family Story, 3 p. (Box 3)
    - Draft, "Benjamin E. Wilson," 2 p. (Box 3)
    - Draft, "Sandra Browning," 4 p. (Box 3)
    - Outline, "Guero," 3 p. (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Drafted Pages (Box 3)
- II. SHORT STORIES/PLAYS
  - Untitled, 30 p. (Box 3)
  - Play, Ten Strangers, 1963, 22 p. (Box 3)
  - Play, Ten Strangers, 1963, 1-13 p.p. (Box 3)
  - Play, The Dark Lens, 42 p. (Box 3)
  - Play, The Dark Lens, Stage Directions (Box 3)
  - Mini Operas (Box 3)
- III. MOVIES/TELEVISION
  - Movie, Outline: Morales vs. America, 18 p. (Box 3)
  - Movie, Screenplay: Carrasco, missing p.p. 1-7 (Box 3)
  - TV, Storyline: Quincy, 1 p (Box 3)
  - Movie, Screenplay: Summerfield, complete 150 p., (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Movie, Screenplay: Summerfield, partial, 150 p. (Box 3)
  - Movie, Screenplay: Copyright Application, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Script, "Feazer," 51 p. (Box 3)
  - Script, "Wildflowers," 73 p. (Box 3)
  - Outline, "Murder by Mail," 9 p. (Box 3)
  - Script, "A Storm of Strangers," 27 p. (Box 3)
  - Outline, "Eldoradoville," 5 p. (Box 3)
  - Proposal, "Golden Missions," 4 p. (Box 3)
  - Synopsis, "Desert Ransom," 4 p. (Box 3)
  - Outline, "Desert Ransom," 4 p. (Box 3)
  - Synopsis, "O'Malley of the Movies," 3 p. (Box 3)
  - Nightmare At Puerto Prieto: Xerox of Typescript, 52 p. (Box 3)
  - Nightmare At Puerto Prieto: Xerox of Typescript with Later Authorial Changes, 108 p. (Box 4)
  - T.L.S. by David Moss, December 1976 (Box 4)
- IV. NEWSPAPER
  - 1960s (Box 4)
  - 1970s (Box 4)
  - 1980s (Box 4)
  - L.A. Times (Box 4)
  - "South Gate" (Box 4)
  - "Women Mariachis" (Box 4)
  - "Street Names: Wilson Avenue" (Box 4)
  - "Alaska and the Bering Straits" (Box 4)
  - "The Cabbie" (Box 4)
  - "West View: Southern California's Spanish Book Scene" (Box 4)
  - "The Cabbie" (Box 4)
  - "Borderline" (Box 4)
  - "Insight Program" (Box 4)
  - "Marriage" (Box 4)
  - "Deauville Film Festival" (Box 4)
  - "Coachella Riots" (Box 4)
  - "It Happened Here," Various, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - "Bronson vs. Floodtine" (Box 4)
  - Ruben Salazar Death (Box 4)
  - Andrew Young (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Articles by REV (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- V. CORRESPONDENCE
  - 1961 (Box 4)
  - 1963 (Box 4)
  - 1964 (Box 4)
  - 1965 (Box 4)
  - 1966 (Box 4)
  - 1969 (Box 4)
  - 1970, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1971 (Box 5)
  - 1972 (Box 5)
  - 1973 (Box 5)
  - 1974 (Box 5)
  - 1975 (Box 5)
  - 1976 (Box 5)
  - 1977 (Box 5)
  - 1978 (Box 5)
  - 1979 (Box 5)
  - 1980 (Box 5)
  - 1981 (Box 5)
  - 1982 (Box 5)
  - 1984 (Box 5)
  - 1985 (Box 5)
  - 1987 (Box 5)
  - 1988 (Box 5)
  - No Date (Box 5)
  - Luther Nichols, 1970-1985 (Box 5)
  - Walter I. Bradbury, 1968-1977 (Box 5)
  - Peter Miller, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - San Diego State University Library (Box 5)
  - Works Sent to Richard E. Vasquez (Box 5)
- VI. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Biographies (Box 5)
  - Resumes (Box 5)
  - Press Releases (Box 5)
  - Interviews (Box 5)
  - Reviews (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Peter Miller Agency Publicity (Box 5)
  - Events (Box 5)
  - Legal Documents (Box 5)
  - Articles, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - REV'S Research (Box 5)
  - Applications (Box 5)
  - Authors Guild (Box 5)
  - Magazines (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)